hey everyone thanks for listening to the
grow your life podcast my name is jared
mikerkowski and if we haven't met yet i
help coaches trainers mentors authors
speakers people that want to grow their
business on the internet live a better
life make more money and have the
business they've always dreamed of now
today i have a guest of mine a coaching
client of mine that i've known for years
her name is jimmy blake
and she helps people live a life with
more joy hope and confidence by helping
them find their voice discover who they
are and build stronger more authentic
relationships helps people discover
what's holding them back
what's stressing them out what's laying
them flat out so that they can move
forward and get unstuck and i don't know
about you but i could use some of that
in my life i'm sure you could as well
welcome jimmy to the podcast how are you
doing today
i'm doing great today jeremiah it's
truly an honor to be on your podcast
because
you have helped me in so many ways
figure out ways to
come become unstuck myself that's
awesome
well i'm i'm excited that you're here
let me let me ask you this just a little
bit what got you into
uh doing what you do
what got you to where you are right now
in this journey you're you're a coach as
well and yeah you're somebody that helps
these people with this but like what got
you here it it it takes a journey to get
you to where you are today it does i've
been a people pleaser and a people
helper ever since i was big enough to
walk me too
and so um
a friend of mine
said this to me a few years ago he said
if you don't heal what hurts you
you're gonna bleed all over others
that's right and uh a good friend of
mine said hey jimmy not all help is help
and so
that really got me curious because i was
running around jugging a juggling a
whole bunch of balls
helping as many people as i thought i
could
and really what i was doing was i was
trying to help out of my own brokenness
and my own need
to feel valued and validated
and i kept finding myself stuck
in the same pattern i would be in a
different situation but it was the same
exact scenario and i'm like
why
do i keep ending up in the same scenario
so i had to get curious
wow could you talk a little bit about
maybe one of those patterns that you
were in because i think people could
relate to that a little bit and and it
helps kind of bridge that gap to what
we're going to be talking about today
for them
without going into any details you don't
want to share okay share whatever you
feel comfortable with yeah
i would find myself saying yes to
everything hey jimmy can you help with
this yes absolutely i can help with that
boy i had so many jobs
that i didn't even have time to sleep
you know
[Music]
burned out found myself stressed out
um irritable and then
i can't even show up for those
that are the most important in my life
my own family wow
or even my own self you know what do i
need what does jimmy need
yes um so
i am a writing instructor and i work
with horses and this huge epiphany hit
me one day
when i'm walking across the arena
because they're like hey jimmy can you
do this yes
can you do this yes so i literally found
myself
going from one program to the other
without even having time for a break
to go use the bathroom get a drink get
some food
wow and one of my co-workers said
something that kind of offended me
but it was very eye-opening
it usually happens
okay
and this is a question he said he said
hey jimmy
and i didn't have time to stop and i
turned and looked and i said
yes
what do you mean
he said stop being so agreeable to
everyone
there you go
that's it
okay so that comes out of our own need
for validation like you're trying to
make yourself feel like
like
you're you're you know you're trying to
earn
people's love
a good girl she says yes she's gonna do
whatever she can
wow
you know i would bet that there's a lot
of people
i i know for a fact that follow me that
listen to this podcast and i hope that
they
listen through to the end of this that
have experienced this i i talk with a
lot of them on my social media
and and here's what i hear often and
maybe you could have some wisdom for for
those people i'd love to here's why i
love this podcast i love that if
somebody's on my social media and
they're like jeremiah i'm dealing with
this issue i can have a podcast episode
i can direct them to that deals with
that exact issue and and so i had a lot
of
mostly women on my podcast
they're just like
man
i don't want to be
uh
rude
and i have so many obligations
and people resp rely on me so much that
i don't think i could ever do what i
desire to do in life
because that's how i've always lived and
i don't want to be
aggressive and say no to people
and i hear that and
in my mind i'm like i want to like go
into coach mode and be like you're going
to just have to get over it but i think
that as somebody who's walked through it
yourself maybe you have a little bit of
a softer way of putting it that might be
able to help them
so i i want to i want to start with
something i wrote down here perfect
before
i can fully connect to others
i have to understand my own spiritual
emotional
and physical needs
and so what i find in life is a lot of
us
especially those of us that are helpers
we've learned how to ignore
what do i need
right
maybe i need
to just take five minutes and go to the
bathroom but if i think you need me that
bad i'll hold off my need
maybe i need to take a ten minute walk
and go clear my mind
and get a drink of water
and just
just have a quiet moment to myself
but if i think you need me right now
and and maybe
you're going to walk away from me
then i'm going to put that need down and
when i keep suppressing those needs
i'm going to find myself in a place
to where i can no longer suppress them
yeah i'm going to be burn out
angry
anxious
sick
yup that i lived my life that way for a
long time
to where like i wouldn't i wouldn't go
to the bathroom and things like that i
had i had read about um
uh complex ptsd
and it was actually that's one of the
symptoms specifically the bathroom
anxiety
of if neglecting to go to the bathroom
uh they have found and this isn't a
diagnosis but it's a it's a symptom to
maybe even talk to a therapist or
something if you find yourself
frequently like just not doing the basic
needs of going to the bathroom because
you're helping other people that can
point to
some severe uh complex ptsd post
traumatic stress disorder from abuse
that we've that we've dealt with and and
so how does somebody heal
in that type of a situation
for me jeremiah started with my horses
yeah
okay
so my horses helped me start to heal
because a horse
they're congruent and what i mean by
that is
their outside energy matches their
inside energy they don't wear a mask
they're congruent at all times they they
they're gonna do what they need to do to
keep themselves safe
yeah okay
um people we can wear masks and so i i
started curious
because with our mustang my husband
could go out
and do certain things with him and i
couldn't
and i was doing the
thing
i'm like what is going on
he's like all over the place dancing
around is he's snorting
you know because
i'm all smiley on the outside and i'm
like hey i just want to fly spray you
but on the inside i'm like what if i do
it wrong
what if i mess him up
what if i don't do it exactly right or
am i holding the rope too tight am i
holding and so i'm having all of these
anxious thoughts and so my
inside energy wasn't matching my outside
energy so he couldn't trust me
yeah
and so what i had to do was i started
with a very simple exercise
and that was learning how to breathe
jimmy that sounds crazy we all know how
to breathe well
maybe not right
no as a writing instructor
you can watch your
the horse and you can tell what your
students doing and when they get nervous
they tense up and the first thing you do
is start holding your breath
that's right i i find myself doing that
all the time still
my wife's like you're not breathing
[Laughter]
and so what i started doing was i just
started practicing this little uh thing
that worked for me like
and i just started doing every morning
when i got up i would just set a little
timer and i'm like i'm gonna breathe
into the count of four i'm gonna hold it
to four
and i'm gonna breathe out to the count
of six and when i started practicing
my morning time
when i would get in a place like working
with a horse i would like oh i'm just
gonna stop and breathe and
what that does
is that brings inner peace to the inside
and so then i would just get in tune
with my horse and he would tell me
when i wasn't in the present moment
because horses live in the present
moment
wow
and then what i started doing with
horses i started seeing
in my everyday life it started spilling
over
that's true i love that that is so cool
and that is how i started
working and coaching with others and
finding that i could bring solutions
that were helping people and not making
them dependent upon me
wow
what is that type of therapy called with
the horses that you that you talked
about that you do
what is it called yeah is there like
like like something that people can look
up or yes so it's like equine
assisted learning
equine assisted learning awesome yeah i
knew there was like a term for it there
is a term it's equine assisted learning
wow and so when we work with horses
here's the beauty of it
and so i actually love working with
people
it works so great with someone who knows
nothing about a horse because if i find
someone that knows a lot about a horse
they're trying to apply horsemanship
yeah i'm not saying that we shouldn't
learn how to become good horsemen
but equine assisted learning is not
about
horsemanship techniques i'm gonna
i'm going to teach someone things they
need to do to keep themselves safe and
i'm going to watch the horse and the
person
ah
but
when you're working with a horse you can
actually be putting a halter on upside
down
and the horse is perfectly fine with it
as long as you're congruent
yeah
that's so interesting
you got me thinking too in just
situations my own life
people
uh people can be like those horses
sometimes
my wife
who
tends to be very like you said like your
husband tends to be
very
uh even keel and she can meet the same
person
who has a completely different reaction
than
they do with me
if i feel intimidated by that person
and it's a completely different
environment type of a thing and it's
kind of like with a horse and i found um
oh about a year ago we were doing some
work with uh with a billionaire and and
some stuff and i felt very intimidated
talking with him and
and uh i had to talk with my therapist
about it i'm like what is going on and
finally i've like worked through that
and now like i have a lot more
confidence in those situations
i found myself in in a safe way
i used to do it in an unsafe way here's
just kind of a story
off of this
unsafely i used to put myself in
situations with unsafe people by myself
to try to work through my issues and i
ended up getting hurt by them
i think some people
do that
in a familiar way like if they grew up
in a family environment that was unsafe
or things like that
um but what i found was if i could
strategically
just
have a little bit of time with somebody
that i felt unsafe with and then monitor
just the one emotion that i felt and
then talk with my therapist about that
one emotion we were able to work through
the issues
piece by piece
instead of me going at it on my own and
so
there's it's so interesting how human
emotion how we react whether it be with
horses or with with people
uh is it's incredible that we can work
through that we can we can grow in that
way
i find it so interesting that you gave
that example yeah okay
um so i want to i want to talk to two
things yeah okay with that
and i know we're doing a podcast but
do you post this live anywhere like
where some people can watch the video
yeah the video will be up yeah okay so
i'm gonna go to the first one i'm gonna
just do a cool little thing here okay
so what do you describe what you see i
just put something on jeremiah
you have sunglasses on with green tape
over the lenses and they're criss-cross
pattern
over there's a smaller tape above and
below like a division symbol but it's
cockeyed crooked diagonally okay
so i do this with people a lot
especially in groups and so i just did a
women's event i had 20 women
so 20 women have on glasses
with duct tape on the front in all
different patterns
okay
this is a perception thing okay
because
we all perceive things a little
differently based upon the way we grew
up
yeah how we process things
okay
yeah um and even though we're doing this
podcast and we are
talking
not everyone may have the perception
that i'm even intending
to send out
because
we have different meanings
of words or because of life experiences
right right
and so the the most hilarious thing
about this is
when i was talking to the women i was
standing in front of a woman and her
glasses had so much tape on them even
though i was right in front of her she
could not sense that i was talking to
her
oh really yes and so the whole place
erupted in laughter
okay
and so
this is why
talking things through
with people is so important to gain
someone else's understanding
and it's trying to be able to see things
from someone else's perspective yeah
and so i love what you were talking
about i'm going to go back to about how
you kind of put yourself
with the unsafe person and you were
trying to identify an emotion and then
you talked it through with your
therapist
okay
which is a safe thing to do
it is a very safe thing too yeah and i
do encourage people because i have
people all the time that ask me you know
people a lot of times call me their
therapist and i'm like i'm not a
licensed therapist right yeah
and i am for if you need a licensed
therapist
you know
i can help you find one i can recommend
one
um i can recommend some resources yeah
yeah but
also one way that i can help people
is to put them in a round pen with a
horse
i had an incident where i was actually
working with a group of uh ladies
and i would put them in the round pen
one at a time
and the lady did not feel safe being in
there with the horse but
i knew that if i could get her to stay
in there and stay connected with me
that i could set her up for success
well
she started to run out of the pen
and i asked can i could i ask permission
can i come in with you
and she said yes
so i came in with her
now she still did the work but just
having me beside her gave her enough
confidence to do the tasks
so she was in what she felt like was an
unsafe situation she wasn't actually in
a physically unsafe situation i want to
clarify
right but mentally she felt she was okay
and so i gave her a task
she was able
to complete it
and the look of joy on her face was so
amazing she came back
the second day
and here's the beauty of it she was able
to do the task
by herself in the round pen wow okay so
what that did is that actually rewires
your brain
that she had the ability
to be in a situation where she felt a
little unsafe
yes she was able
to keep herself safe yeah
now i know that that rewired her brain
and she's gonna carry that forever
that's amazing and that's going to help
her even in her
actual therapy with her therapist
and and i do want to add you know if
somebody is in a situation where they
are legitimately
unsafe it's best to not be in that
situation
what we're talking about like if it
feels unsafe but you know logically it
is it's
it is a safe environment
those are two different things two
completely different things absolutely
yeah um and i find a lot of times
as people i know for a lot of a lot of
years i didn't even know how to
recognize am i in a safe relationship
right
me too that comes from awareness
for me it was friendships that i
struggled with friendships with a lot of
it was it was friendships with other
other men
that i was projecting
a lot of situations from when i was
younger
with my dad into situations and trying
to get validation
and um
it was there's a lot of issues growing
up in the church that we grew up in and
i would kept replaying trying to
basically resolve my childhood with
these toxic legitimately unsafe
relationships i had
you know i had one guy
multiple threats
happen uh just two years ago and that
was right before i started working with
my therapist
uh somebody that i had thought was a
close friend of mine wow um and i was
like like out of nowhere just these
threats i hadn't talked to him in six
months and
started receiving like like and he was
like i actually legitimately felt unsafe
i
ended up having to speak to an attorney
and and figure out my options
because it was like this is not a good
situation and i thought this person was
a close friend
because i kept replaying and attracting
the situations
that i was from my childhood and teenage
years
um
let me let me ask you this
what have you seen in your life
that
when you've done this work yourself
how did this change things for you
well
there's a quote the same little the same
level of thinking that created your
problem won't solve your problem that's
true
okay
yeah so
doing the work um
i'm gonna suggest a book and you
suggested it
nicole
lapera yep how to do the work
and there's also a book by james clear
atomic habits those two books are
incredible we've had those referred on
the podcast so many times
those two books listening to those two
books um
starting to become aware of coaching
with you
there were several times coaching with
you i didn't even realize how i was
presenting myself
right
and so doing the work
learning how to get up
spend some quiet time do some journaling
learn to do some breathing
learning to recognize how i'm presenting
myself
becoming attuned to my own feelings
yeah
and then beginning to see it
in the other relationships in my life
now
i haven't arrived this isn't a place
where whoa you've arrived you're there
this is a
constant life work and what i find is if
i'm not learning and growing
and working
i'm going backwards
yes
and look at you today
being able to talk about this with
confidence and clarity
and and encouraging other people
and having to set strong boundaries
jeremiah
so um it doesn't mean
that um we can have empathy for where
others are
okay and we can listen
but we don't have to give them a seat at
our table
right
exactly
okay yeah and
we've got to learn new ways to work
together yes that doesn't mean that i
have to do everything for everyone
and it doesn't mean that i have to keep
doing the things that the way i've
always done them now it doesn't mean
that i have to just come in strong and
be like
you know
like i worked my way into some of these
patterns and so now i have to gently
have
empathy for others who were in my closed
circle
and kind of undo some of the things to
to be able to set people up closest to
me
he'll live their best life
you know sometimes we make people
dependent upon ourselves
right we didn't mean to
but it's empowering to help them be able
to do the things they need to do and set
them up for success
[Music]
two things you said here i want to maybe
unpack this a little bit
and we'll go back to the question that i
mentioned in the in the beginning um
you have to gently do it with yourself
it's an act of self-care
yes that as somebody who is a pleaser
and a helper
to
be gentle with yourself on this journey
that can be a really hard one
right
that has been one of my hardest ones
because me too i've found that i'm so
incredibly hard on myself
right
and a lot of times we look at ourselves
and we compare ourselves to someone else
and what i find is
i'll compare my worst to someone else's
best
or i'm comparing a skill set that i have
to someone else's and i don't have to
compare that
yeah
and
so learning to be gentle on myself and
saying
you know what um
you're really kind of
messed up today
really didn't realize how you're
presenting yourself you came off
really hard or really strong or really
you didn't need to use the words you did
but that's okay
there you go because you're learning
yeah and a lot of times this happened
with my horses i remember one day
i was trying to
uh do something with my mare
and
i was getting really frustrated i was
getting really frustrated with her and
myself and
i just had a total meltdown out in the
pasture and i'm just kind of
and then i just had to stop and breathe
and you know what
when i stopped and took some breaths and
had a little pep talk with myself
she came right back over and she was
like hey i'm here
we can try this again like she was
willing to forgive me
come back into my circle
yeah and i just
allowed myself to have my moment
cry my tears
and be okay with where i was at the
moment
then her and i could continue with what
we were trying to do
that's awesome
it's a it's
it's a beautiful thing
when we can get there
yeah
i have a question for you okay for those
people that are
saying well i just i have all these
responsibilities these people are
depending on me i have obligations
i have and they always are saying yes to
things and if i don't say yes who's
gonna do it
and we make people dependent on us
this is i think the the this is like the
painful part of the conversation
yeah and i would say if somebody's
listening to this podcast still at this
point i think they're ready to hear this
painful part of it
is
we have to give up
the way that we have been
hurting ourselves to care for other
people
that's a big one jeremiah
and i've done it for years
and what i find is we find ourselves at
levels
like you were able to do it with kind of
a
you know the closer you get to us
there's a close group and then there's a
farther group and there's a farther
group okay
so you you start learning to do it with
those who are more at a distance from
you
if that makes sense okay
um
and it's hard when you first so for
instance
two years ago i got an opportunity to
get a certification and it was going to
be totally paid for
yeah okay
and when i kept praying about it
i kept hearing the lord say you don't
need this
and i really didn't want to say no
and
i just
spent some quiet time
and i kept hearing the same answer and i
had some people around me going
oh that'd be crazy it'd be a crazy
opportunity to give up and i was like
am i going to do this because it's the
right thing for me
it's the right thing for my business
and it's where the lord's leading me
where am i going to do this because i
still am trying to please a certain set
of people
yes
and so i came back
and with gratitude i said i am thanking
you so much for this opportunity what a
wonderful opportunity
you have given me but
as i've prayed about it and thought
about it
this is not for me to do for now
yeah let me tell you what that was
hard and i kind of felt some separation
because some of those that were really
close to me were all going through the
certification
yeah
and
but that was such a freeing moment
yeah
such a freeing moment okay
and uh now i'm going to talk about
something that's even closer and more
personal yeah
on uh
june 13th was my husband's
60th birthday we had a big his daughter
was coming over and we were going to
have this celebration
and i was having some internal pain
and i kept ignoring it
[Music]
i had ignored it for a few hours i just
thought it was having some digestive
upset
okay
mm-hmm it went on for several hours and
it kept increasing
increasing increasing
and so
my husband
picked up that something wasn't right
with me he said jimmy
you're not getting any better
something's wrong
and i'm like oh it's just it's just it'd
be okay he's like no call the doctor
i went to the doctor and she listened
and she said jimmy you have a hot
appendix
oh wow
yeah and um
so
and i think you have an aneurysm in your
belly
it's good that you listen to that
i wasn't prepared for that though
yeah because those closest to me i've
made super dependent upon me i do so
many things for them
guess what when they're rushing you into
emergency surgery
and you don't know what the outcome's
going to be
yep
so as i've been at home and having to
go through a physical and emotional
healing journey
i've had to step back and even for those
closest to me so i'm i'm letting another
barrier down saying
i'm having to go
i've made
some of my closest inner circle my
family so dependent upon me what if i
didn't come out of surgery that day
right
i did and i'm here today in this podcast
and i'm so thankful and i have so much
gratitude but it shows me how we always
have another level to grow
and let me ask you a question on that
by you making others dependent on you
were you helping them or hindering them
hindering them
exactly and yet a lot of people think
that they're helping people by doing
that not all help is help
yeah there you go and there's a dopamine
rush that we get
helping someone and becomes addictive
for years i did not even understand that
and so helping someone felt good
and then i want to do it again and i
want to do it again
yep
but i kind of see it as the caterpillar
becoming the butterfly
the caterpillar has to struggle
it has to go through that time and it
has to go through that pressure
now see here's the thing without
pressure
i'm not going to change that's true
we have to have a certain amount of
pressure
now that's the beauty of working with
horses horses learn
by applying pressure but they learn from
the release of it
wow
okay and and a lot of my clients this is
what they begin to see like they're
trying to get the worst to do something
and their pressure pressure pressure and
there's been no release and the horse is
like looking for the answer pushing
harder trying to make it happen
and what they find is the moment they
just let the release happen
yeah just let go i had a gentleman over
one time he's trying to get the horse to
step in the hula hoop and i said just
take a deep breath
oh he was not attached to the horse
the horse was walking around freely
i said all i want you to do is think
about the horse stepping into the hula
guess what happened
the horse stepped into the loop
wow
and the and then the god turns and looks
at me and he's bawling his eyes yeah
that's all it took
for him to visualize apologizing for
crying
for him to visualize it happening yes
that's so that's so good my you know my
wife whenever i went into this
conversation with that billionaire that
i was talking about she told me i need
you to see yourself
as a billionaire in the future and
you're talking to somebody
respectfully
but that has that
is good enough to give advice to this
person
and you imagine that the outcome is the
best possible outcome yes because our
energy comes across then in that way and
it creates that versus oh i'm expecting
him to not think i'm good enough i'm
expecting him to to do that and i hear
so often people are like you know well
i'm
what good am i i was actually just
speaking to a room of 100 songwriters
yesterday wow um there was and this one
guy said you know well why would anyone
want to listen to me
i'm just a nobody big black man with a
loud voice why would anybody care
oh wow i said as long as you think that
that's all that you're going to get you
got to find that inside of yourself and
he came up to me afterwards and he said
you know what jeremiah after i saw you
speak for an hour and a half you gave me
hope
that i mattered
and that that if i'm just myself people
will love it
because because he's like because i
loved hearing you and you were just
yourself
that's and it's like
like that was i didn't even hear that
and see that transformation in just a
half hour of the of the conversation
from the stage that interaction with him
in the audience um
was inspiring to me to hear
that's powerful it's
it's amazing but as people
were such
energetic creatures
yes human beings are yes we
like the energy that comes across even
the energy that comes across
on camera like there's an energy that
comes across between you and i right now
yes that we can feel
even though we're not in the same
location
exactly
[Laughter]
and with that
like
if
if people business owners specifically
let's just go right down to bottom line
brass tacks their sales would increase
simply by learning this emotional
control of their energy when they go
into a sales situation
yes
you're right being confident and being
happy and being joyful and
expecting the sale but accepting if they
said no
exactly
yep
exactly that's that's exactly right
so one of my clients one of my clients
said this and i i just want to
it was a beautiful moment
because we'd been talking about
relationships what if i could build a
relationship with me myself and i
yeah
she said this client said if i could
build a team with myself
with my heart
my mind and my soul
that would be an amazing team and i
could probably heal
yeah person who said that is doing
amazing things
i see healing
and all of the relationships in their
life
wow able to keep themselves safe and
move forward when they need to
that's so good
what would you say to somebody who's
listening to this right now
if you hear some
noises we got a cat crawling across the
computer here while we're recording
it's okay what would you say to somebody
who who
is in that this situation they they're
resonating with what we're talking about
and
they're like you know
i want to break free from this
besides reading those books you know
what what's some advice that you could
give them
just in closing here to start to live
their life
with more joy more confidence to help
them find their voice
to help them discover what's holding
them back so they can move forward what
would you say to that person
make yourself a priority
make yourself a priority make yourself a
priority
get up earlier in the morning
even if it's only 10 minutes
okay
and i want you to find
a quiet place if it's in your closet if
it's at your table if it's on your back
porch
okay
now you can bring your phone but don't
look at your phone only use the timer on
it yeah and if you have 10 minutes i
want you to set a timer for 10 minutes
okay
there's something that helped me in the
beginning
and i would just try to sit
for three minutes
in silence
three minutes
and it and it would go like this
then my brain would start going i'd be
like oh i'm supposed to be quiet okay
it's okay it's okay jimmy it's okay
it's good i'm just gonna sit silent i'd
set a timer for three minutes now when i
first started this i couldn't even
for three minutes was a challenge for me
right
because i'm like oh i gotta do this i
gotta do that no no no i'm just gonna be
quiet i'm gonna be quiet just for three
minutes
and then i would set a timer for another
three minutes and i'll just practice
breathing
okay
and i would count to four literally one
two three
four hold it
one two three four
breathe out i would count between four
and six okay
and then the last thing
so if you had 10 minutes now
get a notebook
and uh get you a pen out and i want you
to journal for three to four minutes
and i don't want you to judge what you
put on the paper anything that comes to
your mind is free game writing
write it write it write it write it
now if you don't want someone to see
that tear it up throw it away but don't
judge
don't go i can't write that down
let it flow out i find it's like opening
a sore and letting the
the stuff out
when i started that practice
it started helping me now obviously i
like to spend time reading the word but
i would do those things before i start
reading the word and spending time in
worship
yeah
it helped me get clear totally me too
and so i want to i want to read a quote
by christopher robin
okay
you
are braver than you believe
you're stronger than you seem
and you're smarter than you think
wow
that's so good i love that
this has been great i think that this
would be encouraging to a lot of people
that are listening
uh thank you so much for just sharing
your heart here thank you so much for
just sharing this with everybody
you're welcome jeremiah thank you for
what you do
you're
welcome where can people find more
information about you
they can find me on
facebook
okay at
ray of hope ranch
with buddy and jimmy blake
okay you can find me on our website
at
rayofhoperranch.com
all right
rayofhoperanch.com
if you've got a ram hope ranch you'll
you'll be able to find us on facebook
we have a link there so
rayofhopebranch.com awesome
thank you so much and listen if if this
has helped you
if you've listened to this podcast
episode
and and you're just like man i need to
share this a friend of mine that said
help them please share it with somebody
don't let this just
just
take it yourself pass it on
and really
practice some of the stuff that jimmy's
talked about here
as well
i i think if you don't have somebody
that you can talk to about stuff
getting a therapist or finding somebody
who's a safe person
to bounce some stuff off of is so
important
i i keep saying this we're not meant to
be lone wolves in life correct we're not
meant to be i hear so many people say
this well i'm a lone wolf i'm a i'm a
ride or die with myself and ain't nobody
gonna help me succeed and i'm just like
i haven't seen a change in you in six
years either
because you're just spending the same
stories over and over
and i don't mean that to like judge
people it's like
they're almost kind of blinded by that
habit a little bit and they need
something to break that a little bit but
they're scared to because people have
hurt them
so often and people haven't been a safe
place and i totally get that and that's
why
people live their life like that lone
wolf type of
thing i know i did for for a long time
and anytime i would make friends they
would always end up hurting me
and and it took making some real friends
and
listening as well my wife was like hey
maybe those people aren't healthy for
you to hang out with maybe this person
is for me to really realize that
and
i think that if you're listening to this
podcast
and you don't have that
make it
an intentional part of your life
to find some to find some friends to
find some healthy friends you know
there's a book
uh by an author her name is jeannie or
jenny allen
uh jenny allen
two books i love ones get out of your
head
it's a great book but her new book that
she wrote this year specifically after
covid was
find your people
building deep community in a lonely
world
and it she's a christian author and and
she shares how to find people when
people are scary
and that's exactly what the book is
about
is that and i think that it'll really
bless some people listening to this as
well uh as well as the the book by
nicole lapera
and um what was the other one that you
had shared what was the other book
uh james clear atomic habit james clear
atomic habits yeah
how to do the work by nicole lapera
jenny allen find your people and atomic
habits by james claire man those are
like three books honestly if you read
those three books
and your life doesn't change i'm not i'm
not sure what's going to help you focus
something inside of you is going to
change by reading those books in a
positive way and that's the other thing
too maybe
listening to different stuff reading
different stuff if you if all you listen
to is fox news
oh exactly like
that's all you're going to be thinking
about if all you're listening to is
angry people in your community that are
grumpy and angry and upset like that's
all you're gonna be thinking about and
so just changing where you put your
focus
listening to some healthy podcasts
there's over 180 episodes of this
podcast following people like like jimmy
blake online reading some of the books
we recommended those are ways that will
shift the way you think and you'll
notice changes in your life just by
changing what you feed into your brain
it's so true
all right thank you so much for being
here
thanks jeremiah
grow your life everybody and we'll talk
soon have a good one